Register of the Rodolfo Echeverría Martínez Collection, 1911-1986
Hoover Institution Archives
- PARTIDO COMUNISTA MEXICANO, CENTRAL COMMITTEE, 1921-1986
  - Trade union movement and syndicalism. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE
    - General
      - General. Clippings, reports, pamphlets, flyer, circular, directory of trade unions, resolutions, and newsletters; relates to miscellaneous strikes and working conditions, and meetings, including national syndical conferences, 1931-1980 (Folder 2-3)
      - Conferencia Nacional Sindical, 1978 Dec. Discussion bulletins, reports, letters, resolutions, rules, miscellany, declaration and pamphlets, 1978 (Folder 4-5)
    - Central Obrera Independiente. Pamphlet, 1963 (Folder 6)
    - Comite de Defensa Proletaria. Circulars, letter, newsletter; includes material relating to the death of Julio A. Mella and a regional meeting, 1928-1929 (Folder 7)
    - Confederacion de Trabajadores de America Latina. Pamphlets and leaflet, 1945-1964 (Folder 8)
    - Confederacion de Trabajadores Mexicanos. Circulars, convocation, pamphlets and a printed article; includes material criticizing Vincente Lombardo Toledano, 1933-1952 (Folder 9)
    - Confederacion Sindical Latinoamericano. Printed bulletins and newsletters, 1929 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Confederacion Sindical Unitaria de Mexico. Circulars, newsletter, and resolutions, 1929-1934 (Folder 2)
    - Consejo de Coordinacion Sindical. Reports, n.d. (Folder 3)
    - Frente Obrero Comunista de Mexico
      - General. Reports, resolutions, forms, and pamphlets relating to working class conditions, electoral fraud and international affairs, 1956-1962 (Folder 4)
      - La Verdad Obrera. Printed articles and serial issues, 1958-1965 (Folder 5)
    - Frente Sindical Independiente. Newsletters, pamphlets, circular and reports, 1971-1975 (Folder 6)
  - Women. Circulars, newsletters, programs, reports and pamphlets by Ana Maria Hernandez, La Mujer Mexicana en la Industria Textil, and Artemisia Saenz Royo, Historia Politica-Social Cultural del Movimiento Feminino en Mexico, 1914-1950; also includes material relating to a national conference, including a report by C. Valentin Campa, 1931-1980. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE (Folder 7-8)
- PARTIDO COMUNISTA MEXICANO, NATIONAL CONFERENCES, 1921-1982
  - First National Congress, 1921 Dec. Photocopy of constitution and resolutions, and reports (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Conference, 1924 May. Report (Folder 2)
  - Third National Congress, 1925 April. National Executive Committee report (Folder 3)
  - Seventh National Conference, 1932 Jan. Information bulletin, organizational chart, circulars, plans, and resolutions (Folder 4)
  - Sixth National Congress, 1937 Jan. Printed resolutions (Folder 5)
  - Seventh National Congress, 1939 Jan.-Feb. Pamphlets by Hernan Laborde relating to 1940 elections (Folder 6)
  - Extraordinary Congress, 1940 March. Resolutions, discussion materials and a booklet by Dionisio Encina entitled Fuera El Imperialismo y sus Agentes (Folder 7)
  - Conferencia Nacional de Organizacion, 1942 July-Aug. Report (Folder 8)
  - Ninth National Congress, 1944 May. Issue of La Voz de Mexico (Folder 9)
  - Tenth National Congress, 1947 Nov.-Dec. Pamphlets (Folder 10)
  - Eleventh National Congress, 1950 Nov. Report, resolutions, and a convocation (Folder 11)
  - Twelfth National Congress, 1954 Sept. Convocation, reports, and statutes (Folder 12)
  - Thirteenth National Congress, 1960 May. Open letters, reports, resolutions, press release, outline and bulletins (Folder 13)
  - Fourteenth National Congress, 1963 Dec. Resolutions, press release, reports, statutes, and pamphlets (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Fifteenth National Congress, 1967 April (?). Two issues of La Voz de Mexico and a pamphlet by J. Encarnacion Perez entitled Que El Partido Necesitamos (Folder 2)
  - First National Organizational Congress, 1972 May. Letters from Agustin Montiel (in jail) and others, pamphlets by Manuel Terrazas and others, reports, notes and resolutions (Folder 3)
  - Sixteenth National Congress, 1973 Oct.
    - General. Pamphlets, resolutions, discussion bulletins, reports, notes, and a program (Folder 4)
    - Reports
      - Central Committee. Relates primarily to the party program and organizational problems (Folder 5-7)
      - Central Control Commission (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Second National Organizational Conference, 1974 Dec. Clippings, miscellany, pamphlet, discussion materials, convocation, plans, resolutions, notes and reports by Arturo Martinez Nateras and others (Folder 2)
  - Second Extraordinary Congress, 1975 May. Press release, convocation, and information bulletin, 1974-1975 (Folder 3)
  - Seventeenth National Congress, 1975 Dec.
    - General. Convocation, serial issues, speech transcript (Valentin Campa), leaflet, pamphlet and miscellany (Folder 4)
    - Reports
      - General. Reports, relating to the international situation, the Comision Nacional Juvenil and other issues (Folder 5)
      - Central Committee. Resolutions submitted by regional groups, and reports by Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo, Arturo Martinez Nateras and others; includes materials relating to organization and strategy for 1976 election (Folder 6-7)
  - Asamblea Nacional Permanente, Fourth session, 1977 March. Resolutions and an open letter (Folder 8)
  - Eighteenth National Congress, 1977 May
    - General. Agenda, information bulletins, speech transcript, miscellany, lists, proposals and a circular (Folder 9)
    - Reports. Central Committee reports relating to JCM, international affairs, and internal party issues, including Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo, "El Partido Comunista Frente a la Crisis Actual", and "Una Politica para Salir de la Crisis Nacional", and Jesus Sosa Castro, "La Tactica Sindical de los Comunistas Mexicanos"; includes resolutions and commentaries from regional organizations (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
    - Resolutions. Primarily by regional organizations (Folder 3)
    - Salutations and open letters from other organizations, primarily international communist parties (Folder 4)
  - Nineteenth National Congress, 1980 March
    - General
      - General. Miscellany, agenda, printed booklet, lists of delegates and of candidates for the Central Committee (Folder 5)
      - Articles and clippings (Folder 6)
      - Discussion bulletins (Folder 7)
      - Letters and salutations from affiliated groups (domestic and international) (Folder 8)
      - Reports and resolutions
        - General. Includes a report relating to the 1980 election campaign (Folder 9)
        - Central Committee. Drafts and a printed copy of a report by Arnoldo Martinez Verdugo (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Comisiones de Trabajo
      - General. Meeting notes (Folder 2)
      - Statutes. Report and printed copy of statutes (Folder 3)
      - Political theses. Reports, resolutions, and a clipping relating to specific theses and alternative proposals (Folder 4)
  - Twentieth National Congress, 1981 Sept.
    - General. Telegram, articles, transcript of a speech by the delegate from the Italian Communist Party, resolutions from state organizations, and miscellany, 1981-1982 (Folder 5-6)
    - Unification documents. Reports, clippings, resolutions, articles and open letters relating to the proposed unification of five Mexican left-wing organizations (PCM, PMT, PPM, MAUS, PSR) to form the Partido Socialista Unificado de Mexico (PSUM) (Folder 7)
- PARTIDO COMUNISTA MEXICANO, REGIONAL COMMITTEES, 1935-1981
  - General. Instructions, miscellany, letter, reports, and plans; relates to regional activities, meetings and trips, 1976-1979 (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Aguascalientes. Letter and newsletter, 1940-ca. 1966 (Folder 2)
  - Baja California. Circulars, reports, letters, position papers, newsletters, meeting minutes, resolutions, calendars, political platforms, relating to regional conferences and elections, 1972-1980 (Folder 3)
  - Chihuahua. Newsletters, resolutions, conference agenda and reports, 1964-1978 (Folder 4)
  - Coahuila. Circulars, position papers, plans, resolutions, notes, miscellany, newsletter, letters, conference materials, and reports, 1935-1980 (Folder 5)
  - Durango. Report relating to regional conference, 1977 (Folder 6)
  - Guanajuato. Circulars and reports relating to a regional conference, 1977 (Folder 7)
  - Guerrero. Newsletter, reports, and resolutions, relating to regional conferences and electoral campaigns, 1975-1980 (Folder 8)
  - Hidalgo. Action plan, meeting report, and a speech transcript, 1974-1977 (Folder 9)
  - Jalisco. Newsletters, circulars and reports, relating primarily to a regional conference, 1972-1981. (Folder 10)
  - Mexico. Convocation, report and notes relating to meetings, 1976-1977. SEE ALSO: REGIONAL COMMITTEES/Valle de Mexico (Folder 11)
  - Michoacan. Pamphlets, statutes, letter, miscellany, notes, lists and a circular, 1943-1977. NOTE: Most of the materials of the ALCARAZ series relate to the state of Michoacan. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE (Folder 12)
  - Monterrey. Leaflet, newsletter, letters and a flyer, 1935-1979 (Folder 13)
  - Morelos. Plans to build a group in Cuernavaca, 1974 (Folder 14)
  - Nayarit. Newsletter, election material and letters, 1977-1981 (Folder 15)
  - Nuevo Leon
    - General. Resolutions, pamphlets, flyers, reports, speech transcript (J. Encarnacion Perez), and newsletters (Salto), 1962-1981 (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
    - Universidad Autonoma de Nuevo Leon. Draft letter, discussion bulletins, and reports, 1977-1980 (Folder 3)
  - Oaxaca. Correspondence, membership lists, flyers, reports, and newsletter, relating to elections and regional congresses, 1935-1981 (Folder 4)
  - Puebla-Tlaxcala. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE
    - General
      - General. Letters, pamphlets, action plans, miscellany, clippings, reports, circulars, flyers, newsletters, declarations, press releases, forms, notes, lists, interviews, agenda, speeches, biographies, resolutions, and calendars relating to electoral campaigns and electoral reform, regional meetings, internal organization and problems, and regional economic and political issues
        - 1935-1977 (Folder 5-7)
        - 1978-1981 (Box 24, Folder 1-4)
      - Sverdlov (newsletter)
        - 1976 March-1979 Feb. (Folder 5-7)
        - 1979 April-1980 Oct. (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Elections
      - Campaigns
        - 1975-1976. Circulars, letters, flyers, plans, press releases, reports, and pamphlets primarily relating to the 1976 presidential candidacy of Valentin Campa Salazar (Folder 2)
        - 1977. Petitions, flyers, action plans and circulars relating to municipal and federal representative elections and electoral reform (Folder 3)
        - 1979. Letters, circulars, action plans and flyers relating to electoral strategy and a state convention (Folder 4)
        - 1980-1981
          - General. Pamphlets, flyers, press release, circulars, action plans, lists of candidates, sample ballot, forms, and miscellany relating to the second PCM state electoral convention, state and municipal elections, and electoral fraud (Folder 5)
          - Clippings, 1980 July-Sept. (Folder 6)
      - State Electoral Commission
        - General
          - General. Legal statutes and instructions, letters, lists of districts, minutes, forms, press release, and calendar relating to PCM electoral registration documentation, 1978-1980 (Folder 7-8)
          - Correspondence. Letters to Enrique Condes Lara, the PCM representative to the State Electoral Commission, and Luis Ortega Morales, Secretary General of the PCM State Electoral Committee. Relates primarily to meetings (Box 26, Folder 1)
          - Minutes, 1980 June-1981 Jan. (Folder 2-3)
    - Regional meetings
      - First Regional Congress, 1975. Reports, resolutions, notes, circulars (Folder 4)
      - Second Regional Congress, 1978. Agenda, letters, manifesto, reports, list of delegates, circulars (Folder 5)
      - Third Regional Congress, 1981. List of delegates, circulars, discussion bulletins, pamphlet, agenda, reports, press release, resolutions, and clipping (Folder 6)
    - Universidad Autonoma de Puebla
      - General. Circulars, reports, letters, flyers, press releases, action plans, agenda, charts, resolutions, and pamphlets relating to organization, university elections and reform, trade unions and strikes
        - 1974-1980 (Folder 7)
        - 1981 (Box 27, Folder 1)
      - Conferences and meetings. Relates to proposed reform measures, university relations with the community, and other subjects
        - First Congress, 1974 Oct. Reports and resolutions (Folder 2)
        - Second Congress, 1975 April (?). Report relating to the election of the rector (Folder 3)
        - Third Congress, 1977 May. Status report
        - Fourth Congress, 1978 June. Status report, and resolutions (Folder 4)
        - Fifth Congress, 1981 July. Pamphlets, agenda, lists, reports, letters, and circular (Folder 5)
      - Publications. Bulletins, clippings, newsletters (La Hormiga). SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE (Folder 6)
  - San Luis Potosi. Action plan and newsletter, 1972-1976 (Folder 7)
  - Sinaloa. Internal bulletins, newsletters, action plans, position papers, discussion bulletins, pamphlets, resolutions, and reports; includes materials relating to party organization, regional meetings, elections and the Universidad Autonoma de Sinaloa, 1971-1981. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE (Folder 8)
  - Sonora. Status reports, membership list (?), 1961-197? (Folder 9)
  - Tabasco. Program announcements, reports, action plans, circular, newsletter, and resolutions relating to party organization, regional meetings, and the Mexican economy, 1962-1977 (Folder 10)
  - Tamaulipas. Reports, resolutions, action plans, circulars, discussion bulletins, letters, and a flyer; includes materials relating to regional conferences and electoral campaigns, 1933-1977 (Folder 11)
  - Valle de Mexico
    - General
      - General
        - 1971-1976. Circulars, action plans, reports, flyers and letters; includes material relating to the Comision Sindical Regional, regional meetings, electoral campaigns, internal organization, the press and propaganda (Box 28, Folder 1)
        - 1977-1978. Reports, pamphlets, action plans, letters, resolutions, calendar, list and circulars; includes materials relating to a regional conference (Folder 2)
        - 1979-1981. Position papers, reports, letter, and information bulletins; includes material relating to political reform, party organization and development, the 1979 election campaign, and the student movement (Folder 3-4)
      - Conferences and meetings
        - Eight and Fourteenth Regional Congresses, 1975-1977. Reports, information bulletin, delegate list, and a discussion guide (Folder 5)
        - Fifteenth Regional Congress, 1980. Reports, action plans, resolutions, and discussion bulletins (Folder 6)
    - Federal District
      - General
        - Meetings
          - General. Handwritten notes relating to multiple meetings, ca. 1957-1961 (Box 29, Folder 1)
          - Conference, 1956 Aug. Report on organizational problems (Folder 2)
          - Conference, 1957 Aug.-Sept. Notes, resolutions, and a speech by J. Encarnacion Perez (Folder 3)
          - Conference, 1958 Aug. Pamphlet entitled Tesis Sobre el Trabajo Sindical (Folder 4)
          - Conference, 1958 Nov. Discussion materials and reports; includes material relating to the proposed XIII Party Congress, 1958-1959 (Folder 5)
          - Seventh Congress, 1959 March-April. Reports, circulars, pamphlet and copies of printed articles; relates primarily to internal party conflict (Folder 6)
          - Organizational conference, 1960. Convocation (Folder 7)
          - Ninth Congress, 1961 Feb. Convocation, resolution and report (Folder 8)
          - Tenth Congress, 1963. Convocation, resolution, delegate letters, forms and lists, notes, reports, and action plans, 1962-1963 (Folder 9)
          - Organizational conference, 1965. Letters, resolutions, reports, plans, agenda, lists, and discussion report (Folder 10)
          - Eleventh Congress, 1966. Forms, reports, convocation, supplement to La Voz de Mexico, and discussion materials (Box 30, Folder 1)
          - Organizational conference, 1967. Report (Folder 2)
          - Eighth Congress, 1973 (?). Reports relating primarily to organization and programs, 1972-1973 (Folder 3)
          - Fourteenth Congress, 1977. Resolution (Folder 4)
          - Fifteenth Congress, 1980. List of members elected to regional committees (Folder 5)
          - Organizational conference, 1981 Feb. Agenda, delegate list, notes, and resolutions (Folder 6)
          - Seventeenth Congress, 1981 Oct. Reports, letters, and delegate lists (Folder 7)
        - Publications. NOTE: The publications of specific sectional organizations are organized under Sectional organizations
          - General. Flyers, circulars, pamphlets, declarations, and bulletins, 1939-1969 (Folder 8)
          - Vida del Partido, 1952-1964 (Folder 9)
      - Central Committee
        - General. Reports, letters, circulars, resolutions, membership forms, flyer and bulletins, ca. 1941-1980 (Folder 10-11)
        - Political prisoners. Flyer, circulars, letters, and a draft press release, 1961-1966 (Folder 12)
      - Sectional organizations
        - General. Lists, circulars, newsletters, and letters, 1957-1981 (Box 31, Folder 1)
        - Sectional No. 1. Discussion material, resolutions, newsletter, action plans, letter, and reports; includes material relating to regional meetings, 1975-1980 (Folder 2)
        - Sectional No. 2. Circular, newsletter, and a report on party activity, 1977-1979 (Folder 3)
        - Sectional No. 3. Discussion material relating to a meeting, 1977 (Folder 4)
        - Sectional No. 4. Resolutions, pamphlet, newsletters (Conciencia Obrera) and reports; includes material relating to a regional meeting, 1979-1981 (Folder 5)
        - Sectional No. 5. Circular and reports; includes material relating to a regional meeting, 1979-1981 (Folder 6)
        - Sectional No. 7. Reports, circulars, letters, minutes, and newsletters; includes material relating to a regional meeting, 1963-1981 (Folder 7)
        - Sectional No. 8. Reports, newsletters (Formacion), and discussion materials, 1978-1980 (Folder 8)
        - Sectional No. 9. Letters and a discussion report relating to a meeting, 1943-1980 (Folder 9)
        - Sectional No. 12. Newsletter and a report on activities, 1975-1980 (Folder 10)
        - Sectional No. 13. Newsletters, 1980 (Box 32, Folder 1)
        - Sectional No. 14. Lists, minutes, convocation, resolutions and circulars; includes material relating to regional meetings, 1980-1981 (Folder 2)
      - Universidad Autonoma de Mexico
        - General. Pamphlets, newsletters, action plans, circulars, reports, bulletins, resolutions, letters, and discussion materials relating to meetings, 1969-1981 (Folder 3-5)
        - Newsletter (Combate), 1972-1974 (Folder 6)
  - Veracruz. Notices, circulars, plans, position papers, reports, letter, resolutions; includes material relating to elections, regional meetings, and organization, 1976-1977. SEE ALSO: OVERSIZE FILE (Folder 7)
  - Yucatan. Newsletter, plans, newsletters, discussion materials, circulars, and reports; includes materials relating to organization, elections, and regional meetings, 1972-1977 (Folder 8)
  - Zacatecas. Resolutions, pamphlet, and resolutions, 1968-1977 (Folder 9)
- GABINO R. ALCARAZ PAPERS, 1925-1963
  - 1925. NOTE: Papers of Gabino R. Alcaraz, Acting President of the Partido Socialista Michoacano. Letters, form, meeting minutes, and a declaration of principles; relates primarily to membership and local agrarian affairs (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - 1927-1930. Correspondence with the Central Committee and others, financial chart, miscellany, circulars; relates to agrarian issues, the Bloque Obrero y Campesino, and government repression (Folder 2)
  - 1931-1932. Correspondence with the Central Committee and others, circulars and miscellany; relates to administrative affairs, agrarian issues, meetings, the Bloque Obrero y Campesino, and the Confederacion Revolucionaria Michoacana del Trabajo (Folder 3)
  - 1933. Correspondence with the Central Committee and others, flyer, programs, status reports from cells, circulars and a newsletter; relates to the Bloque Obrero y Campesino and municipal elections, international affairs (primarily Europe and Cuba), agrarian and trade union organizations and activities (Folder 4)
  - 1934. Correspondence with the Central Committee and others, circulars, form, newsletter, and a convocation; relates to administrative affairs, the Bloque Obrero y Campesino and elections, international affairs, agrarian and trade union activities (Folder 5)
  - 1935. Circulars, correspondence with the Central Committee and others, reports to the Central Committee, short reports prepared for submission to El Machete, resolutions, newsletter and miscellany. Relates to agrarian organizations, agricultural and trade union strikes, Cuba, the circulation of El Machete, municipal elections and the Bloque Obrero y Campesino, and other subjects (Folder 6)
  - 1936. Correspondence with the Central Committee, El Machete, and others, telegrams, circular, proposal, reports to the Central Committee and miscellany; relates primarily to internal conflict in agrarian organizations (Folder 7)
  - 1937. Letters, resolution, telegrams; relates primarily to local elections and meetings (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - 1956-1963. Letters, memoranda, meeting report, bulletin, and a flyer; relates to internal conflict and meetings (Folder 2)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1919-1983.
  Primarily relates to political organizations and parties other than the PCM
  - General. Pamphlets and issues of Accion Social, Aurora Social, Lucha Popular, Resena de Economia y Politica, and Revolucion Socialista, 1941-1983 (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - Agrupacion de Socialistas Andaluces en Mexico. Notice of meeting and membership forms, 1942-1943 (Folder 4)
  - Asociacion Revolucionaria Espartaco del Proletariado Mexicano. Newsletter (Prensa Obrero), 1966 (Folder 5)
  - Bloque Obrero y Campesino. Circulars, flyer, pamphlet and instructions, ca. 1929-1934 (Folder 6)
  - Movimiento de Accion y Unidad Socialista. Newsletter (Liberacion), 1981 (Folder 7)
  - Movimiento de Liberacion Nacional. Newsletter (El Despertador Obrero), 1964 (Folder 8)
  - Partido Obrero Campesino Mexicano (P.O.C.M.). Flyers, pamphlets, bulletins, declarations, circulars, report, and newsletters, 1951-1960 (Folder 9)
  - Partido Popular Socialista (P.P.S.)
    - General. Letter, declaration, leaflet, flyer, serial issues and pamphlets by Vincente Lombardo Toledano and others, 1957-ca. 1976 (Folder 10)
    - Nueva Democracia. Serial issues, 1967-1970 (Folder 11)
  - Partido Revolucionario de los Trabajadores. Clipping and declaration, 1979 (Folder 12)
  - Partido Revolucionario Institucional (P.R.I.) Report, ca. 1975 (Folder 13)
  - Partido Socialdemocrata. Pamphlet, ca. 1982 (Folder 14)
  - Partido Socialista de Mexico. Copies of printed declarations of principles and program, 1919 (Folder 15)
  - Socorro Rojo. Organizational plan (fragment), and circulars, 1929-1937 (Folder 16)
- OVERSIZE FILE, 1911-1981
  - Newsletters, manifestos, flyers, declarations, election materials and clippings relating to internal affairs, education, trade unions, elections, international affairs, Mexican politics, railroad unions, and regional organizations. Corresponds to the PARTIDO COMUNISTA MEXICANO, CENTRAL COMMITTEE series and the PARTIDO COMUNISTA MEXICANO, REGIONAL COMMITTEES series. (Box 35)